<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!--
<!DOCTYPE book [
    <!ENTITY chapter1 SYSTEM "L1_MusicReading_1.xml">
]>
-->
<!--
  <!ENTITY chapter2 SYSTEM "L1_MusicReading_2.xml>
  <!ENTITY chapter3 SYSTEM "L1_MusicReading_3.xml>
  <!ENTITY chapter4 SYSTEM "L1_MusicReading_4.xml>
  <!ENTITY chapter5 SYSTEM "L1_MusicReading_5.xml>
  <!ENTITY chapter6 SYSTEM "L1_MusicReading_6.xml>
  <!ENTITY chapter7 SYSTEM "L1_MusicReading_7.xml>
  <!ENTITY chapter8 SYSTEM "L1_MusicReading_8.xml>
  <!ENTITY chapter9 SYSTEM "L1_MusicReading_9.xml>
]>
-->
<book id="L1_MusicReading">
<bookinfo>
    <title>Music reading. Level 1.</title>
    <abstract>This eMusicBook is intended to help one improve one's reading skills, providing sort of practice, exercises, and drills that are required in order to become a good sightreader.
        music reding exercises.</abstract>
    <copyright>
        <year>2006-2007</year>
        <holder>Cecilio Salmeron</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
        <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
        under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.1 or any
        later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with no Invariant
        Sections, with no Front-Cover Texts, and with no Back-Cover Texts. 
        A copy of the license is included <link linkend="license">here</link>.
        </para>

        <para>
        The authors have taken care in the preparation of this documentation,
        but make no expressed or implied warranty of any kind and assume no responsibility
        for errors or omissions. No liability is assumed for incidental or consequential
        damages in connection with or arising out of the use of the information contained
        herein.
        </para>
    </legalnotice>
</bookinfo>


<!-- =============================================== -->
<!-- 0. Introduction                                 -->
<!-- =============================================== -->

<chapter id="ch0">
<titleabbrev>Presentation</titleabbrev>
<title>Presentation</title>

<theme id="ch0_0">
<title>Syllabus</title>

<para>
This eMusicBook is intended to help one improve one's reading skills, providing sort of practice, exercises, and drills that are required in order to become a good sightreader.
</para>

<para>Appart of introducing new rhythmic cells, of increasing complexity, the main concepts
introduced in Level 1 are:</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>
    The stave. Treble (G) and bass (F) clefs. Names of notes on the stave. 
    Extension of the stave to include two ledger lines below and above each stave.
</listitem>

<listitem>
    Note values of semibreve, minim, crotchet, quaver and semiquaver, and their 
    equivalent rests. Tied notes. Single-dotted notes and rests.
</listitem>
    
<listitem>
    Simple time signatures of 2/4, 3/4 and 4/4 and compound time signature of 6/8.
    Bar-lines and the grouping of the notes listed above within these times.
</listitem>

<listitem>
    Key signatures of all major and minor keys up to and including two sharps and flats.
</listitem>

</orderedlist>

</theme>

<theme id="ch0_1">
<title>Book organization</title>

<para>
This course has 31 lessons covering the following material:</para>

Music notation basics:
    
Clefs and  y ámbitos:
    En las primeras lecciones sólo se usa la clave de Sol (lecciones 1 a 7) con un
    ámbito muy reducido (e4-g4). Progresivamente el ámbito va aumentando para llegar,
    en la lección 7 a c4-f5.
    En la lección 8 se introduce la clave de Fa en 4ª, de nuevo con un ámbito muy
    reducido (a3;c4) y a partir de ahí en todas las lecciones siguientes
    (8 a 26) se usa indistintamente la clave de Fa y la de Sol, cada una de ellas
    con ámbitos progresivos, para finalizar con dos líneas adicionales por arriba
    y por abajo en ambas claves (Sol: a3-c6 y Fa: a2-e4).

Time signatures:
    En las primeras lecciones (1 a 10) sólo se usa el 2/4. Luego, progresivamente se
    amplia a 3/4 (lecciones 11 y 12)
    y a 4/4 (lecciones 13 a 21). Finalmente se introduce la subdivisión ternaria con
    el compás de 6/8 (lecciones 22 a 26).
    
Key signatures:
    En las dos primeras lecciones sólo Do mayor/La menor. A partir de ahí se introduce
    una alteración (lecciones 3-10). Y en el resto del curso se
    manejan hasta dos alteraciones (lecciones 11-26).


</theme>

<theme id="ch0_2">
<title>Lessons' structure</title>

<para>With exception of the firsts lessons, oriented to introduce the basic concepts of
the musica notation, the remaining lessons are structured into three sections:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>In the first one the new concepts and rhythmic patterns introduced in the lesson
are explained.</listitem>

<listitem>In the second section, optional, the new concepts are compared with known ones, so
that the student can better relate the new material and learn it.</listitem>

<listitem>Finally, in the third section some exercises are proposed to learn and practise
the new concepts introduced.</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</theme>
</chapter>

<!--
    &chapter1;
    &chapter2;
    &chapter3;
    &chapter4;
-->

</book>
