<!-- =============================================== -->
<!-- eMusicBook: Music reading. Level 1.             -->
<!-- =============================================== -->

<theme id="time_signature">
<title>Time signatures</title>

<para>
Most music has a rhythm that you can perceive as a repetitive pattern of pulses. It is easy to
identify these pulses: is what we all do when we clap our hands or
tap our foot while lessoning a song. These pulses are the 'beats' of the music and are the basis to organize the
written music.
</para>

<para>
We said in previous lesson that written music on the staff is divided into parts
named 'measures'. All the measures of a piece of music will have the same number of beats.
Therefore, we must learn that
written music is organized by dividing it into small groups of beats; and these groups
are called 'measures'. 
</para>

<para>
To know how many beats are in a measure, a 'time signature' is placed at the beginning of
the staff, after the clef. The time signature is the two numbers placed above and
below the third line:
</para>

<score width="600" height='100' border="0">
    <score_type>full</score_type>
    <music_border>0</music_border>
    <music>
        (score (vers 1.5)(language es iso-8859-1)
         (instrumento
          (datosMusica (clave Sol)(tonalidad Do)
            (metrica 2 4)
            (texto &quot;A 2/4 time signature&quot; dx:0 dy:80)
            (barra Final noVisible) )))
    </music>
</score>


<para>
The top number tells how many beats are there in a measure, and the bottom number
shows the type of note that gets one beat; for now you must learn that the bottom
number 4 means 'quarter note'. So, the time signature in previous example
says that each measure will have two beats and that each beat will get a quarter
note. The time signature is often called the 'meter' of a piece.
</para>

<para>
Not all beats in a measure are equal: there are strong beats (louder), medium and weak beats.
The first beat of a measure is normally the strongest one and the other beats are weaker.
The pattern of strong and weak beats is what makes rhythmic patterns different; it is important to learn to recognize the time signature when lessoning a piece of music. This may take some practice but it is a useful practice for anyone who
is learning music.
</para>

</theme>
