<!-- =============================================== -->
<!-- eMusicBook: Music reading. Level 1.             -->
<!-- =============================================== -->

<theme id="time_signature">
<title>Time signatures</title>

<para>
Most music has a rhythm that you can perceive as a repetitive pattern of pulses. It is
easy to identify these pulses: it is what we all do when we clap our hands or tap our
foot while listening to a song. These pulses are the 'beats' of the music and are the
basis to organize written music.
</para>

<para>
We said in previous lesson that written music is divided on the staff into parts named
'measures'. Although there are exceptions, in general all the measures of a
piece of music have the same number of beats.
Therefore, we must learn that written music is organized by dividing it into small
groups of beats, and these groups are called 'measures'.
</para>

<para>
To know how many beats are there in a measure, a 'time signature' is placed at the
beginning of the staff, after the clef. The time signature is the two numbers placed
above and below the third line:
</para>

<score>
    <music>
        (score (vers 1.5)
         (instrument
          (musicData (clef G)(key C)
            (time 2 4)
            (text _''A 2/4 time signature'' dx:0 dy:80)
            (spacer 280)
            (barline end noVisible)
        )))
    </music>
</score>


<para>
The top number tells how many beats there are in a measure and the bottom number shows
the type of note that gets one beat. For now you must learn that the bottom number 4
means 'quarter note'. So, the time signature in the previous example says that each
measure will have two beats and that each beat will get a quarter note. The time
signature is often called the 'meter' of a piece.
</para>

<para>
So the time signature is just an arbitrary device to help us to understand and write
the rhythm. But remember that rhythm is something natural that exists by itself in the music.
</para>


<para>
Not all beats in a measure are equal: there are strong beats (louder), medium and weak
beats. The first beat of a measure is normally the strongest one and the other beats
are weaker. The pattern of strong and weak beats is what makes rhythmic patterns
different. It is important to learn to recognize the time signature when listening to
a piece of music. This may take some practice but it is a useful practice for anyone
who is learning music.
</para>

</theme>
