<!-- =============================================== -->
<!-- eMusicBook: Theory and harmony                  -->
<!-- ABRSM Grade Six Music Theory                    -->
<!-- =============================================== -->

<theme id="g6t2_triads_chords">
<title>Triads and Chords</title>

<para>
A chord is any group of notes which are played at the same time.
</para>

<para>
Chords can have any number of notes in them, as long as there is more than one!
</para>

<para>
Chords can have any combination of notes in them, but our ears usually prefer listening to chords which are built to the rules of harmony, rather than just a random selection of notes!
</para>

<para>
These chords are built according to the rules of "tonal harmony". (Don't worry about the names of the chords for now!)
</para>

<!--
<score width="600" height='125' border="0">
    <score_type>full</score_type>
    <music_border>0</music_border>
    <music>
 
C major     G minor     C# dim 7    Neapolitan 6th
C major     G minor     C# dim 7    Neapolitan 6th
            
    </music>
</score>
-->

<para>
Whereas these chords were created by my cat walking across my piano keyboard (he's never studied harmony).
</para>

<para>
cat chord 1     cat chord 2
    

 
</para>

<para>
As we just saw, chords built using the rules of tonal harmony have names. There are a few different methods we can use to decribe chords in words, and we'll take a look at these shortly. Before that, we'll go back to the basics of how to build chords in tonal harmony - using TRIADS.
</para>



<part>
<title>Triads</title>

<para>
A triad is a 3-note chord. Take a note (call it the "root"), add a third and a fifth above it, and you have created a triad. (All triads are chords, but not all chords are triads.)
</para>

<para>
Take a note: We'll take an F: root
</para>

<para>
Add a major third above it: root and major third or a minor third: root and minor third
</para>

<para>
Add a fifth above it to make a major triad: root, major third and fifth or a minor triad: root, minor third and fifth
</para>

<para>
We can also build a triad with a minor 3rd and and a diminished 5th, like this: root, minor third and diminished fifth
</para>

<para>
This is called a diminished triad.
</para>

</part>

<part>
<title>Scales and triads</title>

<para>
Each scale has a group of triads whose roots are each degree of the scale. Here's the scale of C major, in triads:
</para>

<para>
c major in triads
</para>

<para>
Look at each degree of the major scale and see if it produces a major, minor or diminished triad.
</para>

<para>
major minor or diminished
</para>

<para>
This pattern is the same for all major keys.
</para>

<para>
 

Let's do the same with a minor scale - here's the group of triads which exist in A minor:
</para>

<para>
a minor in triads
</para>

<para>
We normally use the harmonic (not melodic) variety of the scale to work out triads in music theory. But in practice, triads from the melodic scale will also be common.
</para>

<para>
! Chord 3 is an augmented triad- rarely used in practice.
</para>

</part>

<part>
<title>Naming triads</title>

<para>
Here are three methods we can use to name triads:
</para>

<para>
1. We can use the letter name of the root of the triad, and then add either "major", "minor" or "diminished" (or "augmented") to it.
</para>

<para>
E.g. C major (or just "C" for short), E minor (or "Em") and B diminished ("B dim").
</para>

<para>
 

2. We can use Roman numerals. Each degree of the scale gets a Roman numeral. We use capitals for major, small letters for minor, and a small circle ° for diminished. (Augmented chords have a + sign, but we don't use them in grade 6.)
</para>

<para>
Major Scales:
1
    
2
    
3
    
4
    
5
    
6
    
7
I
    
ii
    
iii
    
IV
    
V
    
vi
    
vii°

 
</para>

<para>
Minor Scales:
1
    
2
    
3
    
4
    
5
    
6
    
7
i
    
ii°
    
-
    
iv
    
V
    
VI
    
vii°

 
</para>

<para>
3. We can use the technical name of the degree of the scale, plus major/minor/diminished as needed.
1
    
2
    
3
    
4
    
5
    
6
    
7
tonic
    
super tonic
    
mediant
    
sub-dominant
    
dominant
    
sub-mediant
    
leading note
</para>

<para>
The Roman numeral system is the most useful, because it lets us understand the triad in relation to the key of the music, and it's a nice, short way of writing triads. Make sure you learn the Roman numerals!
</para>

</part>

<part>
<title>Naming chords</title>

<para>
Triads are very "theoretical" things - we use them a lot when we analyse music, but we don't see them so often in practice. Triads only have 3 notes, but in real life, chords usually have more than 3 notes. Very often they have 4 notes, but can have many more.
</para>

<para>
The most simple kind of 4-note chord is a triad with the root repeated in a higher octave. (Sometimes the third or fifth of the triad is repeated instead of the root.)
</para>

<para>
The triad of C major: c major triad
</para>

<para>
The chord of C major: c major chord
</para>

<para>
Chords which contain only the notes which already exist in the triad use the same naming systems as triads, so this is C major, or I (in the key of C major).
</para>

<para>
Another kind of 4-note chord is one which has a note added which doesn't exist in the triad, for example this one:
</para>

<para>
Here we've got a G major triad, with an F at the top. F is an interval of a 7th above the root, G, so we call this chord G7, or V7 (in C major). Or we can use the technical name of "dominant seventh" (in C major). Dominant seventh chords are extremely common.
</para>

</part>

</theme>
