<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="no"?>

<book id="intro">
<bookinfo>
    <title>LenMus presentation</title>
</bookinfo>

<theme id="thm0">
<titleabbrev>Presentation</titleabbrev>
<title>Welcome to LenMus Phonascus version 3.4</title>


<para>Phonascus, from Latin 'the teacher of music', is a music education software that 
you can use to practice your music reading skills, improve your aural recognition 
abilities, or just learn the fundamental principles of music theory and language. 
From version 3.1 it includes new functions that, I hope, will end up with full support 
for the creation, display, printing, play back and interactive edition of music scores. 
Visit the LenMus web site for more information about the current status of 
the score editor.</para>

<para>LenMus Phonascus allows you to focus on specific skills and exercises, on both 
theory and aural training. The different activities can be customized to meet 
your specific needs at each moment and it allows you to work at your own pace.</para>

<para>LenMus is structured as a collection of fully interactive textbooks (eMusicBooks), 
including theory and exercises. All exercises are fully integrated into the text. 
Music scores are not just images or pictures but fully interactive operational 
music scores that you can hear, in whole or just the measures you choose. 
This enables you to put concepts into practice with immediate feedback and 
makes the subject matter both more accessible and more rewarding, as you can 
hear, test and put in practise immediately any new concept introduced.</para>

<para>Teaching material is organized into levels, and each level into lessons.
Book <link linkend='#LenMusPage/SingleExercises_0.htm'>Single exercises</link> contains 
some basic exercises for aural training and to practise theoretical concepts, 
such as intervals and scales. Unlike exercises included in the other books, 
you can customize all single exercises included in this book. This 
will allow you meet your specific needs at each moment and to practise 
specific points.</para>

<para>We hope that LenMus become a useful tool in your studies.</para>

<para>The LenMus team.</para>

</theme>

</book>
